<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Microsoft on 7sharp9</title>
    <link>http://7sharpnine.com/tags/microsoft/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Microsoft on 7sharp9</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Dave Thomas</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 13:24:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://7sharpnine.com/tags/microsoft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>New Adventures</title>
      <link>http://7sharpnine.com/2016/05/31/new-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 13:24:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://7sharpnine.com/2016/05/31/new-adventures/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So today was my last day at Xamarin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to move on and have some fabulous new adventures.  I don&amp;rsquo;t know quite where this will lead me yet but its going to be exciting finding out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-you-may-ask&#34;&gt;Why? you may ask.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working for Xamarin since 22nd October 2013 on F# tooling and engineering.  Over a period of time it&amp;rsquo;s very easy to become comfortable and complacent and no longer be challenged.  I have a hacker mentality, I need to create new things, crack difficult problems, experiment.   There are various other reasons too, but with the Microsoft acquisition now seemed as good a time as any to say goodbye and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-next&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a nutshell, I will also be writing, live-streaming and working on my own new and wonderful things to challenge myself and push my boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll once again available for some consulting work too, so feel free to ping me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reckoning day</title>
      <link>http://7sharpnine.com/2015/07/16/2015-07-16-reckoning-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://7sharpnine.com/2015/07/16/2015-07-16-reckoning-day/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;img-left&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/256/18984716933_b7f2cbe6fb_t.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

I&amp;rsquo;ve finally been awarded a &lt;a href=&#34;https://mvp.microsoft.com/en-us/default.aspx&#34;&gt;Microsoft MVP&lt;/a&gt; its been quite a long time coming.  Ive been nominated for MVP every year since July 2011 but until now I have been unsuccessful.  On the 1st of July I received an email congratulating me that I had been successful on my MVP nomination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I am now officially a Microsoft Most Valued Professional!&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/271/18984720063_55b4c8d2cf_z.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was first nominated in July 2011 which seems like an age ago.  I have been
nominated various times each year since then.  There are various activities that
I have been involved in over the that last four or so years in F#.  Here are the
ones that I feel particularly proud of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;blogging&#34;&gt;Blogging&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write about various F# topics that I find interesting.  They are usually technical
in nature or just what I find interesting or challenging at the time.  If I can
help someone else figure something out from one of my posts, or bootstrap an
interesting new project, then all the better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;renovating-f-addin-for-monodevelop&#34;&gt;Renovating F# addin for MonoDevelop&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started using F# on OSX the MonoDevelop F# addin was pretty derelict,
it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been updated for sometime and didn&amp;rsquo;t even compile.  It took quite a
learning curve but I soon got up to speed and managed to improve things bit by bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor support and general tooling can take a lot of time and effort, you can often
get stuck on things with no clue on how to resolve something without digging deep
within the F# compiler.  Im sure Don Syme has a spam filter on my emails by now :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;f-on-ios&#34;&gt;F# on IOS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around January 2013 I managed to get F# working on iOS devices, you can read some
of the details in &lt;a href=&#34;http://7sharpnine.com/posts/monotouch-and-fsharp-part-i/&#34;&gt;part one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://7sharpnine.com/posts/monotouch-and-fsharp-part-ii/&#34;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt;.  It was really exciting to get
a shinny new platform availably for F#!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;edge-fs&#34;&gt;Edge.fs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the FSharp.Compiler.Service even came to light I heard about &lt;a href=&#34;http://tjanczuk.github.io/edge/#/&#34;&gt;Edge.js&lt;/a&gt; and
wanted to have F# support, so in May 2013 I set about implementing it.  I
ended up playing around in the compiler trying to figure how things worked.  You
can read all about that &lt;a href=&#34;http://7sharpnine.com/posts/i-node-something/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;f-for-scriptcs&#34;&gt;F# for ScriptCS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around June 2013 &lt;a href=&#34;http://scriptcs.net&#34;&gt;ScriptCS&lt;/a&gt; was getting a great deal of publicity on Twitter so I
decided it was about time F# should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://7sharpnine.com/posts/can-i-have-some-fsharp-with-that/&#34;&gt;part of it&lt;/a&gt;.  This was also another
opportunity to start hacking in the compiler again, ultimately this ended up with
better programmatic REPL support added to the F# compiler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;creation-of-f-compiler-service&#34;&gt;Creation of F# Compiler Service&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of working on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fsharp/xamarin-monodevelop-fsharp-addin&#34;&gt;F# plugin&lt;/a&gt; for MonoDevelop it came to light that better
support was needed for the F# compiler so that better tool integration could be
built.  I worked to try and consolidate different areas of the the compiler that
were being used by disparate tooling at the time.  This eventually lead to working
with Don Syme to create &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Compiler.Service/&#34;&gt;FSharp.Compiler.Service&lt;/a&gt;.  Over time this repository has
been improved and lead to even better tooling for all editors and IDE&amp;rsquo;s that use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fsharp-core-nuget-package&#34;&gt;FSharp.Core nuget package&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I petitioned for some time to get better PCL support for F#, namely the quite
common profiles 78 &lt;em&gt;(.NET Framework 4.5, Windows 8, Windows Phone Silverlight 8)&lt;/em&gt;
and 259 &lt;em&gt;(.NET Framework 4.5, Windows 8, Windows Phone 8.1, Windows Phone Silverlight 8)&lt;/em&gt;.   Once
the extra profiles were brought to fruition I created a nuget package to deploy
them for easy consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;f-community-bad-ass&#34;&gt;F# Community Bad Ass&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of my favorites:  In May 2014 I was awarded the F# community Badass
award at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/FSharpLondon/&#34;&gt;Functional Londoners&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/7sharp9&#34;&gt;@7sharp9&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fsharporg&#34;&gt;@fsharporg&lt;/a&gt; &amp;quot;For services to the F# community in open source, cross-platform IDE, mobile and runtime tools&amp;quot;. Badass #1&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Don Syme (@dsyme) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dsyme/status/464669331889340416&#34;&gt;May 9, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had got an official trophy for that, it would have looked really good on
the mantlepiece!  :-)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/256/18984716933_b7f2cbe6fb_z.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Until next time &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>